Guide to the Patriotic Envelope Collection [1861-1865], 1898 PR 117
New-York Historical Society
- Series I: Civil War Envelopes, 1
  - Portraits--C to D: General Dix (Offsite-box 5, Item 5)
    Portrait of John Adams Dix. White envelope with black ink. Image on top-left.
  - Portraits--C to D: Charles Carroll of Carrollton. (Offsite-box 5, Item 1)
    Portrait of Charles Carroll. White envelope with black ink. Image on top-left.
  - Portraits--Davis, Jefferson: Jefferson Davis (Offsite-box 5, Item 80)
    Portrait of Jefferson Davis. Yellow envelope with black ink. Image on left.
  - Portraits--Davis, Jefferson: Is coming: Southern Menagerie (Offsite-box 5, Item 90)
    A circus traveling on the road labeled "to Boston," with animal cages labeled "the striped Davis," and " the old bear-re-gard." White envelope with colored ink. Image on left.
  - Portraits--Davis, Jefferson: The traitor Arnold. (Offsite-box 5, Item 210)
    Jefferson Davis in hell with a devil riding on his back and another at his feet. White envelope with colored ink. Image on left.
    Creator: Hayes, J. E., copyright holder
  - Portraits--Davis, Jefferson: When shall we three meet again Very soon (Offsite-box 5, Item 121)
    Image of the devil with a pitchfork, and Davis, Stephens and Beauregard as donkeys. Davis asks when they'll meet again and the devil answers 'very soon'. White envelope with red and blue ink. Image on left side.
  - Portraits--Davis, Jefferson: Blood money; or how Southern rebels encourage piracy. (Offsite-box 5, Item 5)
    Jefferson Davis, seated, is approached by Confederate soldiers with a Union prisoner and a corpse wrapped in the American flag. White envelope with colored ink. Image on left (vertical orientation.)
  - Portraits--Davis, Jefferson: Old dog Jeff you're a traitor. (Offsite-box 5, Item 230)
    Abraham Lincoln and Ulysses S. Grant sit down to eat a turkey on a drum labeled "Washington." A dog labeled "Jeff" sniffs Lincoln's hand. White envelope with colored ink. Image on left.
  - Portraits--Davis, Jefferson: Jeff Davis' attack on Fortress Monroe. (Offsite-box 5, Item 131)
    Jefferson Davis knocking over a beehive and being attacked by bees. White envelope with brown ink. Image on left.
  - Portraits--Davis, Jefferson: Northern cheese (Offsite-box 5, Item 168)
    Winfield Scott traps a rat labeled "Jeff Davis," in a trap labeled "Northern cheese." White envelope with black ink. Image on top-left.
  - Portraits--Davis, Jefferson: Long may he wave (Offsite-box 5, Item 176)
    Jefferson Davis hanging by a noose in a tree with a serpent wrapped around it. The "Southern Eagle" flies in the background. White envelope with black ink and applied color. Image on left.
  - Portraits--Davis, Jefferson: The flag of the new Confederacy (Offsite-box 5, Item 7)
    A flag showing a foot, labeled "Uncle Sam," kicking the behind of a man labeled "Jeff Davis." White envelope with red in. Image on left.
  - Portraits--Davis, Jefferson: Jeff Davis 'taking' Washington. (Offsite-box 5, Item 217)
    Jefferson Davis taking a photograph of the Capitol Building. White envelope with black ink. Image on top-left.
  - Portraits--Davis, Jefferson: Jeff Davis & Co. "seeing the elephant." (Offsite-box 5, Item 155)
    A charging elephant labeled "Uncle Sam," tosses Jefferson Davis, and a dog labeled "& Co.," into the air. Cream envelope with black ink. Image on left.
    Creator: Kline, A. C., copyright holder
  - Portraits--Davis, Jefferson: This modern Blondin leaves but one impression. (Offsite-box 5, Item 224)
    A man labeled "J. D." walks a tightrope over a waterfall with the U.S. Capitol on one side and a man with an axe about to cut the rope on the other side. White envelope with brown ink. Image on top-left.
  - Portraits--Davis, Jefferson: Dictator Jeff. (Offsite-box 5, Item 231)
    An ape sitting on a throne saws the tail off of a cat labeled "Virginia.: White envelope with black ink. Image on left.
    Creator: Brown & Ryan, copyright holder
  - Portraits--Davis, Jefferson: My little Kentucky "Breck." (Offsite-box 5, Item 233)
    Jefferson Davis making a marionette of John Breckenridge dance. White envelope with blue ink. Image on left.
  - Portraits--Davis, Jefferson: To the rescue of sacred soil (Offsite-box 5, Item 1)
    Henry Wise riding a horse with the skull and crossbones on its neck, shouting "to the rescue of the 'sacred soil'." White envelope with blue ink. Image on left.
  - Portraits--Davis, Jefferson: Jeff. Davis going to war. Jeff returning from war an- (Offsite-box 5, Item 115)
    Jefferson Davis with the caption above "Jeff. Davis going to war." when the envelope is inverted the image looks like an ass and the caption above "Jeff returning from war an…" White envelope with black ink. Image on top-left.
  - Portraits--Davis, Jefferson: The Washington grape (Offsite-box 5, Item 158)
    A fox with a blue coat labeled "J.D." & a confederate flag tail looks hungrily at a bunch of grapes hanging from an arbor. White envelope with black ink and applied color. Image on left.
    Creator: Rogers, E., copyright holder
  - Portraits--Davis, Jefferson: A grave wish. (Offsite-box 5, Item 207)
    Headstone labeled "Jeff Davis, alone." White envelope with blue ink. Image on left.
  - Portraits--Davis, Jefferson: On the last "platform" of the Southern Confeder-ass-y. (Offsite-box 5, Item 195)
    Jefferson Davis hanging by a noose. White envelope with black ink. Image covers sheet.
  - Portraits--Davis, Jefferson: This tells its own story. (Offsite-box 5, Item 8)
    A hand, labeled W. S. reaches out to catch a tiny man with wings carrying the pirate flag, labeled "J.D." White envelope with black ink. Image on top-left.
  - Portraits--Douglas, Stephen Arnold: President, Step. A. Douglas, Vice President, H. V. Johnson. (Offsite-box 5, Item 7)
    Portrait of Stephen Douglas, surrounded by flags and eagle. Cream envelope with black ink. Image on left.
  - Portraits--Douglas, Stephen Arnold: S. A. Douglas (Offsite-box 5, Item 1)
    Portrait of Stephen Douglas. White envelope with black and red ink. Image on top-left.
    Creator: Raynor, S., manufacturer
  - Portraits--E to F: Everett envelope. (Offsite-box 5, Item 3)
    Portrait of Edward Everett. Yellow envelope with red ink. Image on left.
  - Portraits--E to F: Floyd off for the South. (Offsite-box 5, Item 1)
    Floyd on galloping horse carrying bags of money. Tan envelope with black ink. Image on left.
    Creator: Harpel
  - Portraits--Ellsworth, Elmer Ephraim: [Ellsworth's tomb] (Offsite-box 5, Item 2)
    Liberty (?) standing at Ellsworth's tomb. White envelope with black ink and applied color. Image on top-left.
  - Portraits--Ellsworth, Elmer Ephraim: Col. Ellsworth, the martyr. (Offsite-box 5, Item 1)
    Portrait of Elmer Ellsworth. Cream envelope with black and red ink. Image on left. Blue stationary with portrait of Brownell enclosed.
  - Portraits--Franklin, Benjamin: Printing of every description. (Offsite-box 5, Item 1)
    Portrait of Benjamin Franklin on left with text and decoration advertising Dodge & Grattan, Commercial Printers covering sheet. Verso: American flag with text on top-left. White envelope with colored ink.
    Creator: Baker
  - Portraits--Franklin, Benjamin: [Benjamin Franklin] (Offsite-box 5, Item 2)
    Portrait of Benjamin Franklin inset over Liberty and the American eagle. Cream envelope with black and red ink. Image on top-left.
    Creator: Dodge & Grattan, printer
  - Portraits--Fremont, John Charles: We stand by the Union. (Offsite-box 5, Item 2)
    Portraits of Jesse B. Fremont and John C. Fremont with crossed American flags between them. Cream envelope with colored ink. Images on top.
  - Portraits--Fremont, John Charles: Major General John C. Fremont (Offsite-box 5, Item 1)
    Portrait of John C. Fremont inset over image of Caucasian soldiers killing Native Americans. Another view shows a battle between soldiers and Native Americans. Cream envelope with black ink. Images on left and top.
    Creator: Whittemore, J. M., & Co.
  - Portraits--G to K: The Union must and shall be preserved. (Offsite-box 6, Item 18)
    Portrait of Andrew Jackson. White envelope with black ink. Image in center (vertical orientation.)
    Creator: Tilton, J. E. & Co.
  - Portraits--G to K: Lieut. John T. Greble. (Offsite-box 6, Item 2)
    Portrait of John Greble surrounded by flags, eagle, weapons. White envelope with colored ink. Image on top-left.
  - Portraits--G to K: We've nailed our colors to the mast. (Offsite-box 6, Item 9)
    Man nailing the American flag to the top of a mast. Pink envelope with colored ink. Image on left. Embossed decoration on seal. Addressed to John J. Coger, 480 Water Street, New York City.
  - Portraits--L to R: Gen. Lyon, of Missouri. (Offsite-box 6, Item 7)
    Portrait of Nathaniel Lyon that, when viewed horizontally, looks like a muzzled animal, perhaps a dog. Cream envelope with blue ink. Image on left.
  - Portraits--L to R: Sixth Regiment Mass. Volunteer Militia. (Offsite-box 6, Item 1)
    Portrait of Luther Ladd with the American flag flying behind him. White envelope with colored ink. Image on left.
  - Portraits--L to R: Russell envelope. (Offsite-box 6, Item 25)
    Well-dressed (David Allen ?) Russell looking worried as he talks to a boy carrying papers. Orange envelope with black ink. Image on left.
  - Portraits--L to R: Col. Corcoran, Col. Mulligan, Col. Meagher (Offsite-box 6, Item 17)
    Portraits of Michael Corcoran, James A. (?) Mulligan, and Thomas Meagher. Harps and clover form a decorative border around the portraits. Cream envelope with black ink. Image on top.
  - Portraits--Lincoln, Abraham: (Offsite-box 6, Item 43)
    Image of Lincoln as a pharmacist with symbolic names on the jar and bottles that surround him in an apothecary. Cream envelope with red and blue ink. Image on left side.
    Creator: Upham, Samuel C. (Samuel Curtis), 1819-1885, copyright holder
  - Portraits--Lincoln, Abraham: Old Abe. (Offsite-box 6, Item 15)
    Portrait of Abraham Lincoln. Blue envelope with red ink. Image on left side.
    Creator: Whipple, G. M. & A. A. Smith
  - Portraits--Lincoln, Abraham: President--Abraham Lincoln Vice-President--Hannibal Hamlin (Offsite-box 6, Item 48)
    Image of Lincoln in a decorative border with an eagle on top and flags draped below. Another image of Lincoln chopping wood outside his log cabin. Orange envelope with black ink. Image on left side and top of envelope.
    Creator: Zahm, S. H. & Co.
  - Portraits--Lincoln, Abraham: Champion prize envelope, Lincoln & Davis in 5 rounds. 4th Round. (Offsite-box 6, Item 4)
    Winfield Scott and William Seward in boxing ring in which Lincoln fought Davis. Lincoln stands outside the ring as Union army retreats. Cream envelope with black ink. Image covers sheet.
    Creator: S. Raynor, manufacturer
  - Portraits--Lincoln, Abraham: Champion prize envelope, Lincoln & Davis in 5 rounds. 1st Round. (Offsite-box 6, Item 1)
    Abraham Lincoln and Jefferson Davis in boxing ring. Outside the ring on Lincoln's side are Union troops with cannons, generals, statesmen; on Davis' side are generals, statesmen, cotton, dogs, slaves. Cream envelope with black ink. Image covers sheet.
    Creator: Tingley, J.H., publisher.
  - Portraits--Lincoln, Abraham: President Lincoln and his Cabinet. (on back) (Offsite-box 6, Item 39)
    Portraits of all named men in a decorative pattern with shields and flag bunting and an eagle decorating the envelope. Cream envelope with black, red and blue ink. Image is oval on front of envelope, with title on the back.
  - Portraits--Lincoln, Abraham: Champion prize envelope, Lincoln & Davis in 5 rounds. 2nd Round. (Offsite-box 6, Item 2)
    Abraham Lincoln and Jefferson Davis in boxing ring. Lincoln tears Davis' coattail and pants-seat as Davis flees and stumbles. Union and Confederate spectators comment. Cream envelope with black in. Image covers sheet.
  - Portraits--Lincoln, Abraham: Lincoln Pills and Bragg Grapes (Offsite-box 6, Item 42)
    Bullets as pills and grape clusters. Yellow envelope with blue ink. Image across top half of envelope.
  - Portraits--Lincoln, Abraham: His mark (Offsite-box 6, Item 9)
    A flag bearing the image of a foot, labeled "A. L.," kicking the behind of a man labeled "J.D." White envelope with red ink. Image on top-left.
    Creator: James Gates, publisher
  - Portraits--Lincoln, Abraham: Agricultural implements going South. (Offsite-box 6, Item 6)
    Farmer carrying rifle and sword and pulling cannon. Cream envelope with black ink and applied color. Image on left.
  - Portraits--Lincoln, Abraham: Champion prize envelope, Lincoln & Davis in 5 rounds. 5th Round. (Offsite-box 6, Item 5)
    Lincoln stands inside "the champion belt" beside a pyramid labeled with all states. Outside the ring, four men, labeled east, west, north and south, waive hats. Flag, Liberty and eagle above. Cream envelope with black ink. Image covers sheet.
  - Portraits--Lincoln, Abraham: Uncle Abe.-- (Offsite-box 6, Item 46)
    Davis riding a hobby horse while Lincoln sits on a stool and watches him. Cream envelope with blue ink. Image on left side.
  - Portraits--Lincoln, Abraham: Uncle Abe (Offsite-box 6, Item 38)
    J. Davis and A. Lincoln on a see-saw with Davis flying up in the air. Cream envelope with blue ink. Image on left side.
  - Portraits--Lincoln, Abraham: President - Abraham Lincoln. Vice-President - Andrew Johnson (Offsite-box 6, Item 41)
    Dual oval portraits of Lincoln and Johnson with flags and an eagle atop them. Yellow envelope with black ink. Image on left side, motto across top.
  - Portraits--Lincoln, Abraham: The peoples' candidate for president, Abraham Lincoln. (Offsite-box 6, Item 21)
    Portrait of Abraham Lincoln surrounded by flags and a liberty cap. White envelope with black ink. Image on left.
  - Portraits--Lincoln, Abraham: [Portrait of Abraham Lincoln] (Offsite-box 6, Item 52)
    Portrait of Abraham Lincoln in an oval with a decorative border. Cream envelope with black and gold ink. Image on left side.
  - Portraits--Lincoln, Abraham: Champion prize envelope, Lincoln & Davis in 5 rounds. 3rd Round. (Offsite-box 6, Item 3)
    Abraham Lincoln and Jefferson Davis in boxing ring. Lincoln holds Davis off the ground in a headlock. Confederate spectators flee. Mortar shells litter the ground. Cream envelope with black ink. Image covers front of envelope.
  - Portraits--Lincoln, Abraham: Star of the North, or the Comet of 1861 (Offsite-box 6, Item 45)
    Lincoln's head as the falling comet in a starry sky. Cream envelope with red and blue ink. Image on left side.
  - Portraits--Lincoln, Abraham: For President, Abraham Lincoln (Offsite-box 6, Item 50)
    Image of Lincoln. Cream envelope with black ink. Image on left side, and printing across the top.
  - Portraits--Lincoln, Abraham: The Federal Union--it must and shall be preserved. Andrew Jackson (Offsite-box 6, Item 49)
    Portraits of Lincoln and Hannibal Hamlin. Orange envelope with black and red ink. Image on left side.
  - Portraits--Lincoln, Abraham: "Whatever our politics, the Constitution must be sustained." (Offsite-box 6, Item 35)
    Portrait of Abraham Lincoln surrounded by American flags. White envelope with colored ink. Image on top-left.
  - Portraits--Lincoln, Abraham: Big thing. (Offsite-box 6, Item 36)
    Jefferson Davis and Abraham Lincoln in front of the U.S. Capitol Building. Cream envelope with blue ink. Image on top-left.
  - Portraits--Lincoln, Abraham: Secession! Non est. (Offsite-box 6, Item 24)
    Portrait of Lincoln over a shield with the American flag on it. White envelope with multicolored ink. Image on left side.
  - Portraits--Lincoln, Abraham: Secession! non est. (Offsite-box 6, Item 24)
    Portrait of Abraham Lincoln over the American Seal. White envelope with black ink and applied color. Image on left.
  - Portraits--Lincoln, Abraham: Abraham Lincoln is the man for the crisis. (Offsite-box 6, Item 27)
    Portrait of Abraham Lincoln and American flag. White envelope with colored ink. Images in top corners.
  - Portraits--McClellan, George Brinton: Maj. Hen. G. B. McClellan. (Offsite-box 6, Item 3)
    Portrait of George McClellan surrounded by arch with names of great generals, Liberty, Justice and flags. Haldimand Putnam and Elmer Ellsworth stand on either side of arch. White envelope with colored ink. Image on left.
    Creator: Whittemore, J. M. & Co.
  - Portraits--McClellan, George Brinton: McClellan is some pumpkin. Ha! Ha! Ha! Yes. (Offsite-box 6, Item 24)
    Portrait of George McClellan wringing his hands and looking to one side. White envelope with red ink. Image on top-left.
    Creator: Hedge, F.
  - Portraits--McClellan, George Brinton: A Blower (Offsite-box 6, Item 26)
    Wise blows through a tube into a contraption while McClellan looks on with sword drawn. Cream envelope with blue ink. Image on left side.
    Creator: Robinson, A. S.
  - Portraits--McClellan, George Brinton: Gen. McClellan and his staff. (Offsite-box 6, Item 25)
    Portraits of George McClellan, Maj. Van Vliet, Gen. Barry and Maj. ( Robert?) Clarke. White envelope with black and green ink. Image covers sheet.
  - Portraits--McClellan, George Brinton: McClellan, The Napoleon of America (Offsite-box 6, Item 30)
    McClellan on a horse rearing up with his saber drawn and held aloft. Cream envelope with black ink. Image on left side.
  - Portraits--S to Z: Sherman's Flying Artillery. Virginians Retreating (Offsite-box 6, Item 1)
    A cannon barrel with wings flying in the air with a man sitting atop it. People retreat on horse and in carriage. Cream envelope with black ink. Image on left side and bottom.
  - Portraits--S to Z: Art Ward's Speech at Camp Dennison (Offsite-box 6, Item 8)
    Caricature of Ward in top left corner, with entire 'speech' written complete with misspellings and mocking southern accents, in small wrap around text on the front of the envelope. Cream envelope with blue ink.
  - Portraits--S to Z: Maj. Gen. Wool (Offsite-box 6, Item 21)
    Portrait of General Wool.
  - Portraits--S to Z: Camp Dennison near Cincinnati (Offsite-box 6, Item 7)
    Image of the camp with tents and an American flag waving overhead. Cream envelope with blue ink. Image on entire back of envelope with space for an address.
  - Portraits--S to Z: "Secession! Peaceable secession!… (Offsite-box 6, Item 9)
  - Portraits--S to Z: Yancey, Commissioner from "C.S.A." (Offsite-box 6, Item 24)
    Strutting, dandified Yancey with a walking stick. White envelope with blue ink. Image on left side.
  - Portraits--S to Z: The War For The Union (Offsite-box 6, Item 3)
    Rendering of Siegel (Sigel) in a circle with American flags and shields surrounding. Beige envelope with brown ink. Image is patterned on entire envelope, portrait on left side and text on top.
  - Portraits--S to Z: Wigfall on his promised descent on Washington (Offsite-box 6, Item 10)
    Wigfall as a Native American with a hatchet in his hands and a loincloth on. Cream envelope with red ink. Image on left side.
    Creator: Reagles & Co.
  - Portraits--S to Z: Brigadier General,… (Offsite-box 6, Item 20)
    Caricature of Gen. Wise with a spyglass on the shore. He is emaciated with a swollen stomach. Cream envelope with brown ink. Image on left side.
  - Portraits--S to Z: Artemas Ward having had his "Wax Figger Show" 'fiscated, is taken before Jeff. Davis by the Vigilance Committee. (Offsite-box 6, Item 25)
    Caricatures of three men, one leading another blindfolded man (Ward). Cream envelope with black ink. Image on left side.
    Creator: King & Baird, printing
  - Portraits--S to Z: Vice Prest. Stephens, C.S.A. (Offsite-box 6, Item 5)
    Caricature of Stephens looking like an actor with arms outstretched. Cream envelope with blue ink. Image on left side.
  - Portraits--Scott, Winfield: Gen. Scott.--I say, Uncle Sam, it is hardly worth while to use this, it will soon play itself out. (Offsite-box 6, Item 62)
    Gen. Scott stands with Uncle Sam with a candle snuffer near a candle labeled Secession. Cream envelope with blue ink. Image on left side.
  - Portraits--Scott, Winfield: Brave in the Field-wise in Council-a true Patriot-Loyal to the Constitution and the Union (Offsite-box 6, Item 4)
    Portrait of Gen. Scott. Cream envelope with brown ink. Image on left side.
  - Portraits--Scott, Winfield: About This Time You Will Hear Thunder (Offsite-box 6, Item 50)
    Gen. Scott's head blazing through a starry sky as if it were a comet, leaving a trail behind it. White envelope with blue ink. Image on left side.
  - Portraits--Scott, Winfield: I think you've SAUCE enough, sly bird (Offsite-box 6, Item 60)
    Gen. Scott as an eagle with a plumed generals hat on stands on the Constitution with a saber across it. A crow sits on a bale of cotton next to a keg. White envelope with red and black ink. Image on left side.
  - Portraits--Scott, Winfield: In a tight place. (Offsite-box 6, Item 57)
    Gen. Scott flattens figures in a press, one is J. Davis. White envelope with blue ink. Image on left side.
  - Portraits--Scott, Winfield: Past, Present, and Future. (Offsite-box 6, Item 69)
    Gen. Scott with a halo of stars sits at a table with a map of the North overtaking the South, with George Washington behind him. Cream envelope with red and blue ink. Image on left side.
  - Portraits--Scott, Winfield: As It Is. As It Will Be. (Offsite-box 6, Item 49)
    An open hand with names of Davis, Floyd, Stephens, Cobb & Bragg on each finger, followed by a closed hand with heads coming up out of the top of the fist. Pink envelope with black ink. Image on left side.
  - Portraits--Scott, Winfield: "This is my last Campaign, and it shall be my best." (Offsite-box 6, Item 6)
    Portrait of Gen. Scott in a circle with the title surrounding him. On points emitting from the circle are the initials of every state in the Union and Confederacy. White envelope with blue and black ink. Image on left side.
  - Portraits--Washington, George: [George Washington riding a horse.] (Offsite-box 6, Item 112)
    George Washington riding a horse. A broken cannon is visible behind him. Multicolored ink on white envelope. Image on left side.
  - Portraits--Washington, George: Southern Chivalry. Richmond Va. (Offsite-box 6, Item 115)
    A statue of Washington on horse with an African American sitting on his shoulders and waving to a crowd. An American flag is visible in the background. White envelope with red and blue ink. Image on left side.
  - Portraits--Washington, George: Washington (Offsite-box 6, Item 1)
    Oval portrait of George Washington. Cream envelope with purple ink. Image on left side.
    Creator: J.E. Hayes
  - Portraits--Washington, George: [Image of Washington being looked upon by others] (Offsite-box 6, Item 2)
    Image of Washington being looked upon by Native Americans, Liberty figure with a fort in the background. Multicolored image on white envelope. Image on left side.
  - Portraits--Washington, George: One of the rebels. Geo. Washington (Offsite-box 6, Item 3)
    Oval portrait of George Washington. Cream envelope with black ink. Image on left side.
  - Portraits--Washington, George: Washington's Farewell Address. (Offsite-box 6, Item 117)
    Portion of Washington's Farewell Address in a laurel border. Cream envelope with blue ink. Image on left side. Addressed to Mr. R. Heber [Newtone], 21 Ormond Street, London. Stamps and cancelled post marks date this to July 27, 1861.
  - Portraits--Washington, Martha: One of the Rebels Martha Washington. (Offsite-box 6, Item 137)
    Portrait of Martha Washington. Cream envelope with black ink. Image on left side.
  - Satan: Jeff and Beauregard on their last ride. (Offsite-box 4, Item 17)
    Two devils running, one carries "Gen. B" under his arm the other "J. D." under his arm. Pink envelope with blue ink. Image on top-left.